故事都有头儿
Every story has a beginning,
宇宙的故事也是
even the story of the Universe.
大约137亿年以前
Some 13.7 billion years ago,
一件神秘的事儿导致了宇宙的发展
a mysterious event forced the Universe in to motion,
大爆炸
in the Big Bang.
最终产生了各个原子 各个恒星
The ultimate creation every atom, every star
甚至各个星系
and every galaxy.
我们想说说
But this is our story,
数千年来我们如何形成的宇宙观
how for thousands years we piece together a vision of the Universe,
通过科学的方法
made sense through science
探索我们的周围
and discover our place within it.
关于大爆炸事件之后的每个事件
This is our story of everything,
从萨满教到科学家
from Shaman to scientists,
我们将讲述宇宙大爆炸
beyond The Big Bang.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
历史频道·宇宙第一季第14集 宇宙大爆炸
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：射手网 调校：TIAN@CMCT 招募Q号: 76846146
数千年来我们收集  记录的天文数据
For thousands of years we gathered our observations of the heaven
写成书的话  可以堆满一个图书馆
into books that would more than fill a library.
推导出了宏伟的宇宙大致模型
We build a vast body of knowledge about our Universe.
它如何形成
How it all began,
又会走向何处
and how it will End
工作还在继续
It is a work in progress.
推演还在进行
The script still is being written
纸上墨迹未干
and the ink still is wet on the page.
从哪儿开始呢？
Where do we began?
咱们从头
let's begin
开始
at beginning.
从
Let's  begin
大爆炸开始
with The Big Bang.
大爆炸是宇宙进化理论
The Big Bang is a theory of cosmic evolution.
说明了宇宙的参与和如何变化
It tell us how the Universe evolved, how it changed
在那一瞬间之后
from a split second after whatever
原来有什么 又产生了什么
brought it to the existence.
我们还不知道
and still we do not know what that is
直到今天
until today.
当你观察宇宙的时候
When you look out  the Universe
看看其他的星系
and look the other distant galaxies, you see that all is flying away from us
它们都在离我们远去
they all moving outward,
跑的还挺快
at huge velocity.
想像一下 把它们全拉回来
You string that all the way back.
在某一时间
You see the one time, maybe
大约130-140亿年以前
13 or 14 billions of years ago,
整个宇宙不可思议地指向一个点
everything was must be compress  in an inconceivably dense point.
我们知道的并不详细
We know we do not have the whole story
物理学总是由知道的并不详细开始
but we ever have whole story in  the history of the physics.
随着实验方法越来越好
We have series better and better of approaches
越来越多的有趣的事实验证了
rebuilding , start building more and more  beautiful and interesting truths.
大爆炸是宇宙起始理论
The Big Bang is ours theory for the beginning of the Universe.
长期以来
But for a long time,
人们即不考虑宇宙的起源
people neither did not think about the origin of the Universe
也不假定宇宙是无始无终永恒的
or they assumed the universe had always existed and was ever lasting.
甚至科学家们也是
Even the scientists, they were reluctant
勉强 尴尬地面对大爆炸理论
at first to embrace the Big Bang.
有人嘲笑这个术语
It was meant to be a derisive term
大爆炸理论是个矛盾
However, the Big Bang is really a contradiction
它既不大
because it wasn't big
也没有爆炸
and it was no Bang.
说它不大 我们认为
It wasn't big because we think that the Universe
宇宙的开始得有点儿奇异
started of a singularity of some sort
说它没有爆炸是因为当时没空气传播震动
And it was no Bang because  there was no air to carry the vibrations.
理论有点道理 这名儿可不怎么样
So Big Bang is in some sense a misnomer but the name stuck.
总算是个理论
And so has the theory.
这个理论现在已经是基础理论
Right now Big Bang theory is a solid part of science we understand it.
有人硬不接受这个理论 肯定被大家按疯子对待
Anybody who do not accept it will be regard  by  most of the community as a crackpot.
但接受和理解是两会事儿
But acceptance and understanding they are two different things.
理论还不能给出
The Big Bang theory doesn't yet provided
所有的科学答案
all the answers science seeks,
解释宇宙是如何形成的
to explain how our Universe was born.
宇宙学家说起这个理论
When cosmologists refer to talk about the Big Band theory,
解释的都是爆炸以后的事
it is really on description of aftermath The Big Band.
理论没有解释
The conventional Big Bang theory say anything about
任何爆炸之前的事
what Bang, why Bang
为什么发生了爆炸
or what happened before Bang.
现在 在这个时刻
Right now, at this very second
我们在大爆炸发生之后
we're in the aftermath of the Big Bang.
我们所看到的 听到的
Everything what we see, and hear,
尝到的 闻到的和触到的 都在大爆炸发生之后
and taste, and smell, and touch is aftermath.
宇宙的扩展证实了大爆炸理论
The Big Bang is really our evolving, expanding universe.
我们大部分时间在研究我们的星球
For us, mostly stuck on our rocky little planet
宇宙的故事从地球开始
the view of the Universe begins with the Earth.
这就是地球
This is the Earth.
金属内核外包着岩石和氧气
Silicon and oxygen based with metallic core.
表面大部分是水
The surface is mostly water.
充满生物  每24小时自转一圈
It teems with life and rotate once every 24 hours
围绕叫太阳的恒星
while orbit the star called sun
每365天转一周
every 365 days.
这是太阳  主要由氢和氦组成
This it is the Sun. Mostly hydrogen and helium.
表面温度约一万华氏度
Its surface  temperature it is nearly 10,000 degrees F
太阳每秒转换7亿吨的氢
For  energy our sun convert 700 million tons of hydrogen
成6.95亿吨的氦 来产生能量
into 695 million tons of helium every second.
太阳系形成于45亿年前
The Sun is part of the Solar System,
太阳是太阳系的一部分
Formed around 4.5 billion years ago,
还包括地球和其它七个行星
that includes the Earth and 7 others orbiting planets.
从水星到海王星
From Mercury to Neptune.
它不是静止的
And it isn't a static system.
太阳系在转动
Our Solar System is spanning,
以每秒134英里的速度
flying thought space at 134 miles per second.
在太空旋转
Turning in circles.
作为繁星中的一部分
As part of a vast collection of stars and star systems.
和其它大约2000亿个星星
There are maybe 200 billion stars
一起组成了银河系
in this collection called Milky Way Galaxy.
和大约60亿个
And assumed  6 billions of these stars
与我们相似的星球群
with planetary system like ours.
太阳系绕着银河系的中心
Our Solar System orbit the center of the Milky Way,
在偏外一点儿的轨道上旋转
on one of outer arms.
银河系和1250亿个其它星系
The Milky Way is one of more than 125 billions of galaxies,
组成了我们的宇宙
that make up the observable Universe.
这就是宇宙
This it is the Universe.
非常 非常的大
It is really really big.
还会更大
And it's getting  greater.
还在膨胀
it is expanding.
假如宇宙在膨胀 那它以前肯定小点儿
If the universe is expanding, then it used to be smaller.
更小点
Much smaller.
事实上如果时光倒转我们就能看到它的收缩
In fact, if we were backing time, we could watch it shrink.
够远了
That's far enough,
宇宙已经比星系小了
and Universe would be smaller than a galaxy.
再到 已经比太阳系小了
Back , and the Universe smaller than our Solar System.
远远地到回去 整个宇宙有房子般大
Further back and everything exists fits inside a studio,
杯子般大
a coffee cup,
原子般大
an atom.
137亿年前
13.7 billion years ago
宇宙比最小的原子还要小
the Universal was smaller than the smallest part of an atom.
小到不能再小
Unbelievably small.
接着
Then something happened.
闪电中东西全炸出来了
In a flash, each thing suddenly expanded.
就是这么开始了
This was how all began
东西一下子全有了
the first moment of the existence,
这就是我们说的
what we now called
大爆炸
The Big Bang.
我们知道这是真的 可不只是理论推导的
That's what we know it's be true,  not because theories be invented
有所有的观察结果
but because all the observations result.
我们看到的
We can predict the abundance of light elements
和我们预测的相符
they agree over 10 orders of magnitude over what we see.
宇宙的基础就是膨胀
So the fundamentals picture of Universe is expanding,
到回去 挤压
emerging,  got a hot ,
形成又重又热的宇宙
dense universe, find that time in the past
大爆炸就是这个样子
it is the the Big Bang picture.
这个理论可不是一天就清楚的
The theory of Big Bang isn't sort of  thing you can figure out over night.
一年又一年
It takes years.
集中了数个世纪的智慧
Centuries of accumulated wisdom.
人类经过了长时间的思索
Mankind  has been thinking about it for a long time.
甚至都没意识我们在思索
Even before we realized , we were thinking about it.
每次看星星时都在想
Everytime we looked at stars, we will thinking about it.
这些知识我们怎么得到的呢？
How do we know what we now know?
我们怎么弄清楚的呢？
How do we figure it all out?
这是我们的核心内容
That is the heart of our story.
宇宙观是如何行成的
The story of how ours concept of the Universe evolved.
我们集中了人类
We stock pilled the discoveries of the most
最聪明的发现 不懈地努力
brilliants members of our species, allowing us
慢慢地在知识的
however strain and whatever struggle it involves
长梯上攀登
to slowly ascend the ladder of knowledge.
可能我们无能
Maybe compensating the fact, anyone of us
解决不了所有的问题
it's just too stupid to figure it all out
耶 咱们从哪儿开始？
So where do we began?
现在天文学家和物理学家
Today, professional astronomers and physicists on camps like
麻省理工的
the Massachusets Institute of Technology
英国剑桥的
and Cambridge University in England
都在讨论大爆炸
wage debate about the Big Bang theory.
但讨论早就开始了
But the conversation began a long time ago.
甚至在没人知道大爆炸之前
Before anyone ever heard about The Big Bang.
在没人知道什么是天之前
Before anyone knew what heaven is really were.
早在科学存在之前
Away before that science exist
甚至思想成型之前
or with even contemplation in the mind of anybody
人们就探寻我们的起源
people asking questions about origin.
古人看着天空
When early man look at the sky
看着带来温暖和生命的太阳
He saw dominated it by the warming , life giving sun
晚上看着月亮 星星
At night, he saw the Moon and the stars.
这就是宇宙--混乱 严厉 折腾人
This was the Universe -- harsh, hostile and chaotic.
太阳在天空升起 落下
With a drifting sun shifted cross the sky
季节由暖到冷
the season one from warm to cold
古人要了解周围的世界
The primitive people needed to understand their world
才能生存下来
in order to survive it.
人们控制不了大自然
People has absolutely no control of the nature.
为平衡自然的善 恶
The balance of expected and unexpected made people
人们神话了大自然
make nature into Gods
这样人类和大自然就有了关联
in order to establish some kind of relation with them.
没有望远镜这样的现代观测设备
Without telescopes as modern observatories
古人依靠简单的建筑
primitive people relies in the simple structures
来了解天空
to help them to understand skies.
英国的巨石阵
At places like Stonehenge, in England
墨西哥的奇琴伊察
or Chichen Itza, in Mexico
人们认为可以连接天
they attemped to connected into heaven
这个神仙的地方
the perceived home of the Gods.
这是简易的观测设备
This were simple instruments of observation
和分析工具
and tools of analysis
用来了解 解释自然
that help to make sense for dancing  universe
我们在德国东部 柏林南部700公里
We are here is Eastern part of Germany and 700 km  south of Berlin
这个小村叫古斯科
in a little village, called Gosek.
一个专为太阳和星星建的建筑
One of the oldest monuments, dedicated to the sun and stars
被在这儿发现
it was found here.
这是这儿的太阳观测设施
This is the solar observatory of Gosek.
建于7000年以前
It was build 7000 years ago,
是早期农民用来测节气的
and was used by early farmer to tell the time of the year.
比巨石阵早2000年的建筑 重建在这儿
Constructed 2000 years before Stonehenge  and reconstructed here
是欧洲最早的日历
this is the Europe oldest known calendar.
从冬至到夏至
During the winter and summer solstices
从最短的到最长的一天
the shortest and longest day of the year
落日通过门照在不同的地方
the setting sun lights up with gate in the parlances.
当时的知识
The knowledge of days
使人们了解了带来生命的太阳
helped this people understand the life giving sun.
天上是个表
The nice sky  is a clock.
通过这个看着你的表
it is a gigantic clock staring you at face that  allowed the ancient
古人算计着何时种 何时收
to calculate when to plant, when to harvest.
换句话说即对太阳和天空的了解
In other words, they are very livelihood depended on their understanding
决定着生计
of the motions of the sun and the heavens
天文学就是基于天体的运动
This idea of astronomy predicting the behavior of the natural world
预测自然行为的
based on the motion of the heavens,
和占星术的教条混在一起的
gets mixed with the dogma of the astrology
天体的运动被认为可以预测运气
the belief that the motion of heavens predetermined our fate.
流星预示着军事胜利
That meteor signal military victory.
有个新星 肯定有皇帝出生
A new star, the birth of a king.
当时天文学预测星星的移动
Back there astronomy was predicted the motion of stars.
占星术则预测星星对我们的影响
Astrology was predicted how the stars effected us.
古人分不清这两者
And it's real hard in the ancient may to separate this two.
你能看懂天上的表 当然你能掌握自己的命运
If you understand the clock works on heavens  you understand how our fate are going to be.
早在公元前6世纪 占星家把天分成几块
The astrologers divide the skies in regions as early as 6 century B.C.
依照星星的形状
They saw shapes in the stars
给出不同的名字
and named the regions after the shapes.
白羊座
Aries
金牛座
Taurus
还有双子座
and Geminis
和其他星座
among others.
占星家用不同的故事代表不同的命运
But the astrologers give a story sky to divied their fate.
他们也在观察和了解天体的运动
They also watched and learned how the heaven moved.
从迷信到简单的
From superstitious models comes to baby steps
科学观察
of the scientific observation.
科学就象是旅行
I see science as a journey
我们人类
that ours species has been on for
在2500年前就以最大的可能
roughly 2500 years to try to contiguous
了解宇宙
deep way as possible with the universe
宇宙的定理 结构 事物
the laws of the universe,  structure of the universe, what make things up
宇宙如何参与 强制和控制变化
how they evolve and what's their  force, their govern changes.
有时简单的观察
But sometimes, the simple observation
会产生基础性错误
can leave fundamental worry conclusions.
当你观察宇宙时
When you look out the Universe
第一观点是我们是地球的中心
the first sight you get is we are the center of the earth,
一切都是围绕着我们旋转
that universe is revolved around us,
星星滑过夜空 太阳跨过白天
Stars goes cross the night sky, the sun goes cross the day,
就象是大地是固定的 而天空绕着我们旋转
and the sight was the Earth was fixed and the heaven was rotated about us.
这可不对
But that perception is completely wrong.
地球不是固定的 也不是什么中心
Earth is not fixed, it is not the center of anything.
宇宙学的历史
The whole history of cosmology
就是地球从中心撤退的步骤
it is the relentless retreat of Earth from center stage.
无论如何历史是前进的
Nevertheless, the gathering of knowledge move forward.
光用数学方法
Using the mathematics
古希腊人给出了不少
The ancient Greeks provided more detailed information
我们邻居太阳和月亮的信息
about our dominant celestial neighbors  the Sun and the Moon.
2000年之前 他们就知道地球有曲率
Even back then, 2000 years ago, they knew the Earth curves.
看着影子 他们算出了地球的大小
By look at the shades, they calculated the size of the Earth
偏差只有10%
to within about 10% accuracy.
他们算出了地球到月亮的距离
They actually calculated the distance from  the Earth to the Moon
大致估算了地球到太阳的距离
and rough dimension of the distance from the Earth to the Sun
就是说古人一点儿也不差
so in other words, the ancient were no fools.
古希腊人区分了两类星辰
The ancient Greeks also recognized 2 types of stars.
大部分星个儿小 移动时一起动
The most was fixed and small and moved together.
有几个大的 移动的比较奇怪
A few were larger and moved  half-hazardly so was seem.
就是行星
This were the planets
预测行星的轨迹曾是数个世纪的目标
And predict thire motion become centuries long goal.
仅仅用肉眼在天空观察
With just the naked eye to scan the skies.
希腊只看到五个行星
the Greeks saw only 5 planets
并以他们的神来明名
naming each their Gods.
现代我们所熟悉的是罗马人的命名
Today we more familiar with the Roman denominations:
水星 金星
Mercury, Venus
火星 土星和木星
Mars, Saturn and Jupiter.
古天文学家对宇宙的认识
Ancient astronomy assumed a concept of the universe
由希腊哲学家亚里士多德公元前4世纪提出
proposed by the 4 century B.C. Greek philosopher Aristotle
他认为地球是宇宙的中心
who imagined the Earth at center of the Universe,
太阳 月亮和行星们
with a sun, moon, stars and planets
都围绕着地球
all revolved elegant around it
形成完美的球体
in perfect crystalline spheres.
亚里士多德认为宇宙是有限的 象个大球
Aristotle's universe was finite, it was a big sphere
象个葱头--有好多层的葱头
actually was like an onion, was like an onion with many concept spheres
一世纪的天文学家托勒密
First century astronomy Tolomeo
改进了亚里士多德的模型
Improved on Aristotle
通过认真观察行星的轨迹
by actually trace path of planets.
发现了行星的运动规律
which don't move half-hazardly at all
可以用复杂的圆形来推导
Using complex circular motion calls epicitios
他可以描述运动模式和速度
Tolomeo could predict proscribe patterns and changing velocitys.
也就是说能更好地
In other words Tolomeo's system reliably predicted
预测行星的运动
the future behavior of the planets.
这是人类了解 认识
Another step in man's journey
宇宙旅程的又一步
to understand and control the Universe.
托勒密的模型非常复杂
The Tolomeo's system was extremely complex
所有的行星都在饶圈
it had all this planets goin loops
能符合情况 但是错的
and works builtfuly but was just worry.
能符合情况
The idea that you can predict something
并不能说明你的模型就是对的
doesn't mean you understand fundamental principles behind that.
他的模型没改变宇宙大的模型
Tolomeo's system did not actually review the universe
但他做了尝试
but it did try.
他可以给行星定位
He essentially showed that the positions of planets
也可以算出以前和将来行星的位置
could be calculated for any time past or future
这只是数学的伟大
It was a tour de force of the mathematics understanding.
有趣的是
Interestingly
这个方法竟用了几个世纪
the astronomy seemed to stand still for centuries after that.
事实上自公元476年罗马的兴起
In fact after the claps of Rome in the 476 A.D.
天文学就没了地盘
the astronomy actually lose the ground.
欧洲列国支离破碎
Europe fragmented into smaller powers
失去了大批的希腊学者
and a lot of wisdom of Greek was lost.
数千年后 一个新理论发起了挑战
Thousand years later, a new theory would confront the accepted beliefs
天体是怎样运转的？
about how the heaven worked
使人类向大爆炸理论又近了一步
and would move man kind one step closer to the  theory of the Big Bang
公元十五世纪
During 15 century A.D.
日心说
an idea called heliocentrism,
提出是太阳而不是地球 才是宇宙的中心
claimed  the Sun, not the Earth, was the center of the Universe.
天主教徒慌乱了
This horrified the Christian clergy
这与上帝的国都相矛盾
who felt contradicted the word of God.
如果上帝创造了地球 人是他的影子
If God created the Earth and man his own image
那么地球和上帝的子民
then Earth and its devotee inhabitants
必然是万物的中心
must be the center of everything.
讽刺的是日心说的先锋
Ironically, the champion of the sun center universe
是波兰的宗教学者
was devotee church deacon from Frombork, Poland.
尼古拉·哥白尼
name Nicolas Copernicus.
他是教会的管理人员
He was a cathedral administrator.
工作是收房租 照顾病人
Working to help collect the rents,  helping people who were sick.
闲暇他才是天文学家
But in between he was working on astronomy.
哥白尼闹不懂托勒密的系统
Copernicus was troubled by Tolomeo's  complex heavenly mechanics.
但他找了个好办法
But he found an elegant solution.
把地球从宇宙的中心拿了出来
When he moved the Earth from center of the Solar System
把太阳放在中心
And replaced it with the Sun at heart at all.
当哥白尼让行星饶太阳转时
When Copernicus put the planets  going around the sun
他发现水星转一圈用三个月
He discovered that planet Mercury,  which goes around about 3 months
最靠近太阳
Ultimately fell close to the sun.
土星走得慢 转一圈用30年
Saturn, the slowest planet,  which goes around about 30 years,
远远地在外边
ultimately fell the outside edge.
哥白尼写到 没有其他办法
Copernicus wrote: in no other way
可以象日心说这样
do we find such harmonious connection
合理地解释行星的轨道和周期
between the size of the orbit and its period.
真是太神奇了
That seemed almost magic.
哥白尼还发现地球在自转
Copernicus also insisted that the Earth was rotated
每24小时一周
that it spun completely around its axis every 24 hours.
不是天在动而是我们在动
The heaven did not move, we did.
星辰每晚的运动
The stars chasing across sky each night,
是地球旋转造成的假像
was mearly an illusion created by the rotating Earth.
可能怕教会报复
likely, afraid of Church reprisals.
哥白尼一直没有公布他的理论
Copernicus abstained from to publish his theory
直到1543年 病床上他发布了他的理论
until he was on his death bed in 1543.
但他的书《天体运行论》
But his book Concerning the revolution of celestial orbit
给开普勒铺平了道路
paved the way for Johannes Kepler,
约翰尼斯·开普勒生于1571年
born in 1571
观察科学的先驱
the champion of observational science.
开普勒真是个英雄 他站出来向世界
Kepler was the true hero here, because he was the one really come out, trumpeted to the world
鼓吹 太阳才是中心
the Sun has to be the center.
开普勒有珍贵的天文数据
Kepler had his disposition a trove of astronomical data,
收集于多年的观测
collected through years staring of sky
他整理了数据 根据计算得出
When he checked his observations and did calculations, and realized
不只是太阳应该在中心
that's not only was the sun center of the Solar System
原来认为行星轨道是圆形 也有问题
but the perfect circles were a figment also.
哲学上不通 但符合数据
Maybe it's uglyer philosophically, but it really match the data.
开普勒改善了哥白尼的模型
Kepler improved on Copernicus's system
将行星饶日运行的轨道
by hypothesis that planets traveled
由圆形
not in perfect circles,
改为椭圆型
but in ellipses around the sun.
他的模型得到一个怪现象
Kepler's data  also pointed a strange phenomenon
苦苦思索也未能解决
struggled  but  fault to understand.
当行星靠近太阳时 速度快
As the planets approached the Sun, they speed up.
当他们远离太阳时 就慢下来
for their away, they slow down.
整体来说 太阳在中心
Together, the sun centered Universe
和以不同的速度运行的行星
and the variable speed of the planets,
能最好地解释我们在地球上看到的
best explained what we see here in the Earth.
这还是第一次--日心说
Suddenly and for the first time, the sun centered pictures,
比地心说更好地做出预测
gives better predictions than Earth centered pictures.
拿出你的数据
And you have normal something trace by data,
科学家作出处理
but does something scientist suppose to do
作出预测 真好
which is make predictions, which is good.
一个宇宙的谜解开了 又产生了一个
But it's a cosmic riddle seemed solved, another remained.
开普勒发现太阳可以给行星提速
Kepler saw that the sun influenced speed of planets
这是怎么会事呢？
as they traveled through the space. But how?
在这个问题解决之前
Before anyone address this mystery,
科学和教条在争辩
dogma and science collided.
吵吵闹闹整日不停
in a conflict revibration to this very day.
进入17世纪 意大利天文学家伽利略
At the turning of 17 century , Italian astronomer Galileo Galilei
继承了哥白尼和开普勒的理论
would take the theories of Copernicus and Kepler
太阳才是太阳系的中心
that the sun was center of the Solar System
提供了没有争议的证据
And prove them right beyond any shade of doubts.
他使用了新技术
He did it with a new technology,
改变了历史的进程
that would change the course of history.
望远镜 在某种意义上来说
The telescope, in a some sense, is most blasphemous
是华丽的 有煽动性的
most seditious, most revolutionary and most
革命性的科学仪器
splendorous instrument of science.
科学得到了伟大的礼物
All science received a greatest gift
可以把远处的物体拉近的工具
in this tool bring distant objects close.
有这个发明的出现
Once the idea get out,
有可以找两镜片 保持一定距离
you can take 2 lenses, one open in such a way
放入一个管子做成望远镜
put them in a tube and make a spyglass out of it.
它就象暗夜的火炬
That's bright like wild fire around world as it did.
问题不是谁发明了望远镜
So the issure now is not who got the telescope,
而是怎么去用它
but you now knew what to do with it.
拿他去看别人的窗户？
Would you looking people's windows?
还是用它观察宇宙？
Would you look up and out of the Universe.
伽利略在1609年改进了设计
Galileo improved the design in 1609
自己研磨镜片 做了一个
by grinding his own lenses, and creating one that
空前的放大30倍的望远镜
could magnify in unprecedent 30 times.
他用这个望远镜
And with that telescope for some resaen,  he decided to look at sky,
去看金星的位置
that suppose to in come the sharp of republic of Venice
这一看完全改变了天文学的观点
and what he saw complate changed scope of astronomy.
伽利略看到了最清晰的有细节的
Galileo was treated to the clearest and most detailed
从来没有人看到过的天象
view of heaven that any person had ever know.
通过望远镜伽利略看到成千上万
Through its telescope, Galileo saw thousands more stars
的繁星 充满坑的月亮
a Moon populate with craters
木星有几个卫星
satellites circleing Jupiter
土星有一对大耳朵
Saturn with giant ears.
最伟大的发现当属
Greatest of all, Galileo plainly saw
他发现金星有月相
that Venus went through phases like our moon.
充分证明金星在绕日旋转
Clear evidence that Venus orbited the sun.
证实了日心说
Proved the sun centered system.
第一次证实了哥白尼是正确的
This show in first time that Copernicus was right
地球不是中心 太阳才是
the Earth was not the center of the Solar System, the Sun was.
伽利略用望远镜把地球推出
So Galileo with its telescope
了宇宙的中心 "地球不是什么中心
push earth away from center of the Universe, said: "We are not the center of everything.
只是行星中的一员
We are one planet among others.
宇宙比我们知道的大多了 "
and could be much larger universe than we known."
有哥白尼开了个漂亮的头儿
With Copernicus had assumed for aesthetic reasons
有开普勒做了数学和测量上的推演
With Kepler had deduced  measurement and mathematical
伽利略证实了
Galileo proved.
伽利略看到了
Galileo saw.
伽利略发展了日心说
Galileo reviewed.
古人只能用肉眼观察
The ancient had seen everything could  possible seen through naked eye.
确实需要新设备才能突破
It's really take a new instrument to get beyond that.
望远镜是个转折点
The telescope that was the break point was
分离了古今
between ancient and  the modern's.
数百年来教会认为
Centuries of church dogmas
地球是宇宙的中心
claiming the Earth was the center of the Universe,
现在清楚地知道是错的
with now clearly worry.
天主教正在动荡于
With the Catholic Church still waving
新教(基督教)的分离
for schism of  protestant reformation
伽利略的发现看起来有悖教义
Galileo discovery seemed to undermine scripture.
教会有遭围攻的危险
Dangerous for a Church they felt under siege
这个科学家玄了
Dangerous for the scientist who posting it.
无论如何 天主教徒伽利略
Nevertheless, Galileo, a devotee catholic
1610年发布了他对"虚假信息"的研究
published his observations in the book called The story Messenger in 1610.
奇怪
Surprisingly
开始教会表示欢迎他的观点
the Church welcomed Galileo's findings, at the first.
伽利略开始对自己的观点小心翼翼
Had Galileo been a little more careful
无所适从
with his approach, may got no way with it.
红衣主教巴罗尼的著名语录是
A famous quotation from cardinal Baroni, a predecessor, was
"圣经是教我们如何进天堂的 不是教我们天是如何运转的 "
"The Bible tell us how to go to heaven,  not how the heaven's go."
最终伽利略的失势不是
Ultimately, Galileo's downfall was not his inability
他没有能力表达他的想法
to sway the Church to his way of thinking
也不是他解释的不清楚
but rather his attempt at interpreting scripture
而是于教会的对立
all by himself, independent of the Church.
伽利略崇拜的圣奥古斯汀
Galileo credits St Augustin,
曾说过 "如果你的发现
who said that: "If you find interpretation of scriptures
与圣经相矛盾
which same to be contradicted established knowledge
那你就需要再研究一下圣经 "
then you should reconsider that  interpretation of scriptures".
教会虽同意考虑
But the Church concent with perceived
自我解读圣经
frash its own power,
但不同意给伽利略解读圣经
could not concent the biblical interpretation to Galileo.
1633年 在伽利略出版了一部新书
In 1633, after Galileo publish a new book
[日心学的先锋]之后
champion in the sun centered system.
教皇以异教为由对他审判
The Pope saw him for standing trial for heresy.
强迫他放弃日心论
He forced to giveup all his copernican ideas,
很明显他屈服了
which apparently he did kneeling in front of the tribunal.
尽管他屈服了 他仍悄悄持守他的信仰
In spite of its confession, Galileo quietly hold fast for his beliefs
在软禁下度过晚年
throw out his final years under house arrest
于锡耶纳 佛罗伦萨城外
at Siena outside of Florence.
伽利略是第一个现代科学家
Galileo is the first modern scientist, in the sense that
他引入了望远镜做观察
he actively in gage observations with the telescope
他引入了望远镜证实理论
he actively proposed  theories consistent with telescope
他大胆 胆大地挑战教条
and he dared, he dared to challenge the Orthodoxy at the moment.
随后在1642年他死之前
Shortly before his death in 1642
伽利略不小心发现了开普勒之谜的线索
Galileo inadvertently steped over a clues to Kepler puzzle
有关太阳给行星提速的问题
about the Sun strange influence on planetary motion.
这个线索会帮助下一代
It was a cluse would help pointed future generations
推导出大爆炸理论
pull the theory of Big Bang.
伽利略最后的著作
Galileo's last published work
有关下落物体的性质的对话
dialogue on the properties of the falling bodies.
他注意到下落物体的加速
Which he noticed always accelerated to same rate
于质量无关
no matter what their mass.
但是需要另一个天才
But would take other genius
把这两者连接起来
to connect this two puzzle pieces together
万有引力理论
in a theory of the gravity.
艾萨克·牛顿 生于1643年
Isaac Newton, born in 1643
他解释了行星运动的机理
he explained the mechanism by which the planets moved.
不只是行星运动的机理 是万物运动的机理 从行星
And not just how the planets moved, but how everything moved. From planets
到苹果
to apples.
牛顿有超然的智力 作出了惊人的事迹
Newton was a towering intellect. It is astonishing what he did.
他使科学史上绽放出了
His moment in the history of science is a sharp break
数学的魅力 数学将实际应用于物理宇宙
in which the power of the mathematics it really brought to bear on aspects of the physicial universe.
他给我们指明了用数学
He is what set us down this path of using mathematics
解释宇宙 告诉我们
to describe Universe, showing the maths for some reason
宇宙可以用数学来推导
is the language of the cosmos.
开普勒通过他的数据认为
Kepler observed through these data, the tracked effects the Sun
太阳象一个大磁铁
it acted like a giant magnet.
那么行星是否也是磁铁呢？
Might the planets could also be like magnets?
伽利略理论里的下落物体的速度
Galileo's theorized about the rate  acceleration of the falling bodies.
与质量无关
and he realize is regardless their mass.
总是速度相同
falling objects always fall at same rate.
数年后牛顿在二人的基础上有了发展
But years later, Newton had something  to add to Kepler and Galileo.
牛顿的伟大之处是
The great inside Newton had was
把开普勒和伽利略的理论合并
bring Galileo and Kepler together and to realize that
认为导致物体下落的
the things that make project goes moving  falling the Earth
和导致行星围绕太阳旋转的机理一样
it is same things makes the planets going around the Sun in the skies.
就是说行星是落向太阳
In a sense, the planets are falling towards the Sun,
就象伽利略的物体落向地球一样
just as Galileo's falling bodies fall towards the earth.
秘密是引力
The crack at all is the gravity
神秘地把遥远的物体吸引在一起
that strange action at distance that hold everything together.
牛顿不只发现了引力 还给出了可证明的公式
Newton didn't just observed the gravity, he draw it up as a provable equation
显示引力是能量
showing that gravity was the energy
可以吸引象行星和地球似的物体
the catcher that capture matter, objects like the Earth and the planets
从只有一头高到遥远的太空
from flying head long into interstellar space.
引力作用于宇宙间的一切物体
Gravity, the attractive force that affects all the matter in the Universe.
使其遵循宇宙的规律
give the universe order.
引力是物理学的现象
And the gravity is described by the science of the Physics.
牛顿创立了物理学
Newton created the physics.
他是第一个基于观察 发现基本定理的人
He was the person who first saw the fundamental laws, underneath all these observations.
牛顿的定律几乎解释了万物
The Newton's laws explained almost everything.
牛顿运动定律 万有引力定律
Newton postulated the laws of the motion, the universal rules of the gravity.
他开辟了新的科学领域
He begin a new area in science.
用观测和数学
Using observations and the mathematics
来解释自然的规律
to describe the laws of the nature.
他可以显示苹果掉到地上
He could show the way which apple fell to the Earth
和月亮围绕地球旋转
which directly related the way the Moon follow
是相关的
around the Earth.
因为他知道同一个定律
Because he understood that same laws
使行星围绕着太阳
let the motion of the planets around the Sun
使月亮围绕着地球
let the motion of the Moon around the Earth.
牛顿的著作--"原理"
Newton's  great book, The Principia
显示了潮汐 轨道行星的速度
it revealed the tides, the velocity of orbiting planets
甚至地球的形状
even the shape of Earth
都可以用引力来解释
could be explained through pulling of the gravity
因为任何有质量的物体
because everything with mass
对其他有质量的物体都有引力
it exerts pulling force on everything else with mass.
月亮吸引着海洋
The Moon pulls the oceans,
地球吸引着月亮
the Earth pulls the Moon,
太阳吸引着地球
the Sun pulls the Earth, and closer
所有物体相互接近到一起 产生较强的引力
this objects all to each other, the stronger gravit pulls.
牛顿定律是空前的成就
Newton's principia is such a engulfing work of genius
几乎构成一个困惑的事实
that almost makes up a disconcert fact.
虽然牛顿给出了万有引力定律
Although Newton formulated the laws that they govern the gravity
他没有解释 甚至不知道为什么会这样
He never explained or even understood why it works.
引力 你想想 太奇怪了
And gravity, when you think about it, is bizarre.
想一下 地球怎么知道太阳在哪？
Understanding how the Earth knew where the Sun was?
要去饶它转 太阳要突然没了怎么办？
to go around it, what's happen if the sun suddenly move?
地球该怎么办？
What did the Earth do?
这中间还有其他的东西 他放弃了
This actually distants something with, he give up on it,
说我不担心这个问题
say I'm just not going worry about that question
因为定律是正确的
because the laws work.
物理学家们仍然在探索引力的原因
Although the physicists still stuggle to define the gravity.
牛顿也做了大量的努力
Newton had going far in reviewing it.
两百年只后
Two hundred years later
爱因斯坦达到了牛顿的高度
Albert Einstein would arrive Newton's genius.
不只建立了物理定律
Not only creat new laws at physics
还刷新了宇宙观
but re-inventing the Universe.
爱因斯坦1879年生于德国
Albert Einstein born in Germany in 1879.
可能是有过的最著名的科学家
Maybe is most famous scientist to ever lived.
原由他1905年在瑞士的伯尔尼的成就
because what he did here, in Bern, Switzerland, in 1905.
怕毕业后得不到教师的职位
Fearing secure teaching position after his years as student.
爱因斯坦在专利局找了份工作
Einstein took a job at this Patents office.
他的思考开始了
And then he begin to think.
事实上他思考着空间和时间的革命
In fact, he thought about revolution in space and time.
没有爱因斯坦 我们可能还要苦苦探索
Without Einstein, we may still be strugglling to understand
宇宙的运行机理
how the Universe really works.
我相信你要问谁是20世纪最伟大的科学家
I think if you asked who was  the greatest scientist of 20 century.
大部分人会回答 爱因斯坦
mostly would say: Einstein
我认为部分原因是
I think that is a partly  because of the fact just a natural fascination
他神奇地揭开了时间和空间的自然魅力
with the space and time, in mysteries he solved.
还有部分原因是
But also I think it's partly because
他和其他的科学家社区的人和谐相处
He fitted in the arqueotipica public perception of scientist.
爱因斯坦没有想要带我们去宇宙的起源
Einstein didn't mean to lead us to the origin of the Universe.
想都没有想过
He didn't like even think about it
开始的概念是动态的 有限的宇宙
The idea of the beginning suggested a dynamic,  finite universe.
爱因斯坦更喜欢静态的 无限的宇宙
And Einstein preferred static and infinite one.
从哲学角度讲 他相信宇宙是永恒的
Philosophically, he belive that the universe was eternal,
有始有终
and the universe had have a beginning and a ending,
有点儿美感 但不漂亮
was aesthetic, was not pretty.
宇宙是无限的 永恒的是旧理论
The idea that the Universe was infinitely and eternal was old one.
被象爱因斯坦一样的科学家所接受
It embraced by scientists like Einstein.
很容易让人接受的是宇宙总是存在着的
Because it was easier to think the universe as always existing,
要说是形成的
rather then its having been created.
形成的？怎么形成的？用什么形成的？
Created?  how? By what?
对爱因斯坦来说很不幸
Unfortunately for Einstein,
以他对力 象引力的理解
his new understanding of forces like the gravity
最终推出宇宙不是永恒的
would ultimately suggest the Universe was not eternal.
爱因斯坦的想法很奇异
Einstein's ideas was so bizarre
难以想像可以用于我们的世界
It's almost easy to think them to apply some other crazy carnival world.
还有人认为
But strangers may seem
我们的世界是爱因斯坦的世界
our world is Einstein's world.
过来 过来 不要推 不要挤围好了看清楚
Gather around, gather around!  Don't push! Don't shove! Make sure you get good view.
演出要开始了 你肯定不想误
The show is about start, you don't want to miss a thing.
快来了 女士们先生们 步入爱因斯坦的世界
Hurry, Ladies and Gentlemen,  step right up to Einstein's world.
时期要发生总会发生
Where things are always what they appear to be
但不一定总随人所愿
but not always what you expect.
首先我们来看看爱因斯坦这个人
First, the wonderous Einstein in himself.
出生就少了关说话的那块儿大脑
Born missing the region of the brain that influences the speech
他到三岁才会说话
He did not speak until the age three.
可是管数学和空间关系的
However, his parietal lobe,  responsible for mathematical thought
部分 顶叶 太大了
and space relationships, too large,
使他的脑子比别人宽15%
making his entire brain 15% wider.
注意这个大个的大脑--
Notice the enlarged brain…
爱因斯坦是我们所说的想像大师
Einstein was the master of what we call  the thought experiment.
想像那些说不出来的东西
Thinking through an experiment that you can't literally carry out,
基于你的洞察力思考这一问题
but based upon your insight thinking about it.
有时给我们的宇宙观带来革命
sometimes result a revolution at how we think about the Universe.
1905年爱因斯坦公布了特殊相对论
In 1905, Einstein published his theory of special relativity
探索了时间和空间的交叉问题
which explored the link between space and time.
爱因斯坦的理论没把时间和空间分开
Einstein's theory isn't really separated thing  space and time.
把它们结合了起来 我们活空间时间中
but just one thing,  space-time we all lived in.
他认为空间时间象块儿布
He thought this new space-time as fabric,
空间和时间织在了一切
waving together space and time.
1915年爱因斯坦发展了他的理论一般相对论
In 1915, Einstein developed his  theory about general relativity
修正了特殊相对论
which modified special relativity,
增加了重力和重力对空间时间的影响
to include the gravity and it effects  in this fabric space-time.
欢迎来到重力弹跳蹦床
Welcomes to the bounce trampoline of the gravity!
这是我们的空间时间织物
We take our fabric space-time,
压下
stretched it,
在上面放上重物
and placed heavy weight on it.
看 知道它怎么影响空间时间了吧
See how this worked on fabric space-time!
当我们滚一个球在上面的话
When we rolled the ball cross the fabric
就神奇靠向了
it's magically seem to be drew
重物的质量中心
or tracked to the mass weight of the center.
一般相对论是重力的新理论
The general theory of relativity was a new theory of the gravity
他们说了引力的原因
When they told us the gravity worked
是因为在物体这儿空间时间弯曲了
because space and time are curved in the presence of the matter
可以动态相应
and could respond dynamically,
太空自己在膨胀 由物体制约
space in itself, expand, contracted  in the presence of the matter.
疯狂但真实
A crazy but ture idea.
质量这个术语 被描述成容纳
Mass is a term used to describe  the energy and the matter
物体和能量的容器
the objects contain.
质量大的物体
the larger the mass of object,
对空间时间织物的影响就大
the greater restoration of the space time fabric,
就有大的引力
the stronger effects of the gravity.
引力不是真正的力
gravity is not really a force,
是织物
it is a fabric.
是空间时间的形状
it is a shape of space and time.
我们正在这形状上的弯道上移动
And we just move on the curve of shapes.
要这样作 把你心目中的直线
And the act to do so, takes what otherwise be a straight line to you
弯曲成轨道
bends it into which now you described like orbits,
弹道或是轨迹穿越宇宙
as trajectories, as path ways through the cosmos.
爱因斯坦说甚至光线
Einstein said not even light
也逃离不了引力的作用
could escape of the effects of the gravity.
疯狂的说法
As crazy as it sounds,
在1919年证实
prove conveniently arrived in 1919,
那时天文界有一重大事件
in the form of astronomical large experiment
日食
based on a solar eclipse.
一般相对论认为 假如观察
General relativity said if you look at a star
星体的光线刚好通过太阳时
on the path of light goes right path the sun,
会发现因太阳的引力 光线产生偏移
you would see a shift a little bit  because the gravity of the sun.
亚瑟·爱丁顿想测试一下这个理论
So Arthur Eddington actually went out to test that theory
在1919年日蚀时 拍摄星图
during the solar eclipse in 1919, actually photograph stars.
当太阳被月亮挡着的时候
When the sun was blocked by the Moon
能看到它后边的星群
you could see the stars behind it.
能看到太阳后边的物体
The ability to see objects  they were actually behind the sun
证实了物体是遵循空间时间的
proved that objets could work space-time.
一夜之间爱因斯坦成了超级明星
Einstein became a superstar overnight.
1921年他获得诺贝尔物理奖
He received the Nobel prize of physics at 1921.
但相对论给爱因斯坦打开了潘多拉盒
But general relativity open Pandora box for Einstein.
爱因斯坦理论的推理之一
One of the consequences of the Einstein theory
是宇宙不是膨胀的就是收缩的
was that the universe must either be expanding or must be contracting.
宇宙是永恒的是无法解释的
But setting still be eternal it's not a valid solution.
这可是个问题
And that was a problem.
问题是当引入相对论到静态宇宙时
A problem, because if you introduce mass in the Einstein static universe,
所有的质量会被引力吸引在一起
all that mass will through gravity draw together.
是什么避免了它的发生？
What was preventing this for happened?
当有物体在象布一样的宇宙时 我们知道物体相互吸引
When you place matter in the fabric universe, you know matter attract echo other,
这事儿可不稳定
and the thing is unstable.
为了不使引力毁了宇宙
To keep the gravity for clapping the universe
爱因斯坦假想有个力与引力大小相当 方向相反
Einstein postulated a force equal to and opposite gravity.
它刚好抵消了引力
This constant force perfectly contra gravity
维持了静态的宇宙观
to achieve a static universe.
爱因斯坦在寻找这个宇宙常量
Einstein seached for this cosmological constant
相信就藏在他的等式中
convinced it's hiding in his equations
但他错了
but he was worry.
爱因斯坦对他的信念不满意
If Einstein had the anger of his convictions, some sense
他相信的静态宇宙和
he was recognized that the static universe believed in
他的相对论不兼容
was not compatible with the theory come out with.
实际上相对论指出宇宙不是静态的
In fact, relativity pointed a  idea that universe wasn't static.
是膨胀的
But expanding.
坐下 请欣赏神奇的空间时间项目
Site right down, focus, and enjoy magical space-time projector.
看看四维的宇宙
Watch the universe link by 4 dimensions
在空间时间里的运动
move forward in space time.
爱因斯坦不愿他的理论被嘲笑
Einstein himself didn't want make that prediction, that his own theory was sort of screaming make.
我想这次他可是搞砸了
I suppose is one time on sense career, his career failed him.
他没能解决 两个方向的人
he did make it, the both directions was actually
都在盯这他
staring him in the face.
爱因斯坦的理论不可避免地
Einstein's theory inevitably leaved to the idea of
指向宇宙的起始时刻
a moment of creation.
做个深呼吸 看看爱因斯坦没看过的
Now breath youself for  the part that Einstein couldn't watch!
大家别挤 我们倒一下
stay back everyone as we rolled projector backwards.
象是为难爱因斯坦的信仰
In spite of when Einstein believed
他的理论指出的动态的宇宙
his theory pointed at dynamic universe
这次小多了
that was once much smaller.
宇宙缩小到原子的大小
The Universe shirks down to the size of an atom.
爱因斯坦无法接受 但别人可以
Einstein couldn't make that leap, but others would.
动态的 膨胀的宇宙很好地
A dynamic and expanding universe fitted nicely
被大爆炸理论所解释
in the theory called  Big Bang.
进入20世纪
At dawn to 20 century
爱因斯坦不经意地
Albert Einstein may have inadvertently
使我们讨论
let us to consider the scientific possibility
宇宙起始的科学可能性
that our universe begun.
但宇宙的起源
But the idea of a beginning for everything
有很强的宗教反响
has strong religious overtones.
文化将反思 我从哪儿来？
A culture will ask itself:" where did I come from?"
这是人类的重要问题
It is a very important question for the humans.
因为不知来源 就不知责任
Because if we don't know where we came from, we don't know who we are.
数千年来 世界的起源
For thousands of years the origin of our world
是宗教学者的事 不是科学家的
it was matter for religion scholar, not scientists.
科学与宗教是不同的
There is different between science and religion,
有不同的质疑 不同的观点
they are looking at world in different way, they ask different question.
科学家关心事物如何发生 过程怎样？
Science is asking how things happen,what's process.
宗教关心的是不同的有趣的问题
While religion is asking, as I think is different, interest question.
事物为什么发生？会有什么后果？对世界有什么意义？
Why things happen? Is something going on. some meaning of purpose in the world.
科学和宗教很不一样
Religion and science have been uneasy companions.
但都在积极地追求真理
If only because they seem motivated by same quest for truth.
讽刺的是
So it was ironic.
宇宙起源的先驱
that early champion of objective scientific theory
是普通的天主教牧师
for the origin of the Universe, was the ordinary catholic priest.
扭曲得厉害
And what a strange twist,
科学的方案带有宗教色彩
the science based solutions was appear so religious.
宇宙不是总存在的
That the Universe didn't always existed.
但又得停在起始点
But there was once end in the beginning.
勒梅特教父争论说宇宙是形成的
Father George Lemaitre argued that the Universe was born.
勒梅特是我的偶像
Lemaitre is one of my ideals.
在20年代末30年代初
For few years late 20's and early 30's
他精通于
he was the one who better understood
宇宙膨胀概念
the concept of expanding Universe
介绍了好多探索中的东西
and introduced many of  ideas that still are exploring.
20年代勒梅特研究了爱因斯坦的理论
Lemaitre studied the Einsein's theories during 1920's
形成了激进的思想
and proposed a radical idea
其中之一遭到爱因斯坦的反对
One even the great Einstein would reject,
他说宇宙不是静止的
he said the Universe wasn't static
宇宙是膨胀的
but was actually expanding.
勒梅特不带偏见地研究了爱因斯坦的方程式
Lemaitre studied the Einstein's equations kind of  without prejudices
他发现方程式建议宇宙是膨胀的
when he find this equations suggested the Universe that would be expanding today
过去宇宙要小点儿
and for ever smaller in the past
他决定认真研究研究
he decided take that solution seriously.
假如宇宙是膨胀的 勒梅特想
If the Universe was expanding, Lemaitre reasoned
那么昨天就比今天小
it was smaller yesterday than it is today.
那么最终就会小到不可想像
Therefor it must been ultimaclly, unimaginably small.
勒梅特认为宇宙起始于他称之为
Lemaitre belived the universe begun look what he dubed
起始原子的东西
the primitive atom.
一个无限致密的 热的宇宙蛋
A infinitely dense, hot cosmic egg
在过去的什么时间爆炸了
that some time in the past exploded,
起始了宇宙的运动
Setting the Universe into motion,
带来了一切我们所知道的东西
and leading the formation of everything we know.
当他和爱因斯坦提到时
When Lemaitre told Einstein about this solution
据报道爱因斯坦说
Einstein reportedly said
"数学上是对的 物理上真讨厌"
" Your mathematical is correct, but your physics is abominable ".
但就是这个讨厌的东西
But this abomination
在1925年得到简洁的证实
soon receive compacting corroboration in 1925.
在洛杉矶旁的山上 天文学家哈勃
In mountains above the Los Angels, astronomer Edwin Hubble saw something
通过望远镜观测到的现象 摧毁了爱因斯坦的宇宙静态论
in his telescope that destroyed the Einstein's cosmological constant
带给我们新的宇宙观
and it altered our image of the Universe.
1920年我们的宇宙易于理解
In the 1920's we had very comfortable picture of the Universe.
宇宙就是银河系
The Universe is the Milky Way galaxy.
看看这个跨过夜空的牛奶似的大斜条
We saw this huge slope of milk that it cuts across the night sky
叫银河系 有大约1000亿颗星
called Milky Way, consisted of about 100 billion stars.
方圆10万光年
It's about 100 thousands light years cross.
那就是1920年的宇宙 易于理解
That was the Universe in the 1920's, very comfortable.
哈勃把宇宙抽象深化成
Hubble pure deeper into the Universe
伽利略使用那个时代的
that Galileo couldn't imagined
望远镜无法想像的宇宙
using the more fastigiate telescope in his day.
他显示银河系里有数亿个太阳
He revealed our Sun as one star amount billion within the Milky Way galaxy.
就只有银河系吗？
But, was the Milky Way all there is?
如果这样 到底有多大？
If so, exactly how big was it?
自从有了望远镜
Since sprouted powerful telescopes
天文学家用来观查
the astronomers looking in the sky
他们无法测量天体有多远
but they had no could measures of how far a way things were
除了特别近的星体
exception for very close stars.
为解决这个问题哈勃提出了标准烛
Edwin Hubble solved that problem by come up what's that called standard candle.
一个确定亮度的星体
a star of known brightness.
知道它有多亮 就知道它有多远
And if you know how bright it is, you can measure how far away it is.
因为远的东西就暗一些
because the dimer something appear, the farer way it is.
就象远处的火车的灯要暗些
Just like a train in the distance the light seems dimer,
虽着靠近灯越来越亮
comes brighter, brighter it's approach to you.
哈勃找到一标准烛
Hubble found one of this standard candle,
于一个叫仙女星云的螺旋的星系
within a spiral swirl of stars called  Andromeda Nebula.
人们看到的仙女星云象是灰尘
People saw Andromeda with just visable dust
存在于银河系中
inside the Milky Way.
接着哈勃计算了距离
Then Hubble calculated distance.
他相信这个星系有一百万光年远
then he realized that galaxy is a million light years away.
激动的时刻 他脱颖而出
That was the Eureka moment,  and he had this epiphany.
他坚信仙女星云是一个宇宙岛
He realized that Andrmoeda galaxy was island Universe
就象银河系一样
just like the Milky Way galaxy.
就这一下 宇宙
So, in one instant, the Universe
从原来的10万光年方圆的银河系
from be a comfortable Milky Way galaxy, 100 thousand light years cross
变成了惊讶的宇宙
to become this fantastic universe
可能有方圆十亿光年
perhaps billions light years cross,
这发生于一夜之间
and all happened, in just one night.
仅此足使哈勃不朽
This alone would have assured Hubble's immortality.
他一个人使宇宙
He singlehandedly grew the universe
从一个古雅的星系镇
from a quaint, one galaxy town,
到可能有10亿星系的星系都市
to potentially billions galaxies metropolis.
但哈勃有更深的研究
But Hubble was went further.
在1929通过测量星系的行为
He also measured the behavior of those galaxies in 1929
哈勃推断大部分星系在离我们远去
He come a concluded the most of galaxies moving away from us.
不只大部分 准确说它们不止远离银河系
Not just a lot of them but actually  they moving away of the Milky Way
它们相互之间也在远离
and in fact they moving away from each other.
换句话说宇宙是膨胀的
In other words, the Universe is expanding.
每秒都在膨胀
getting bigger every second.
加入时间能倒转 宇宙定要小些
If you went back in the time, the Universe must been smaller.
基于哈勃测量到的膨胀速度
Based on the speed of expansion that Hubble measured
他能算出宇宙的年龄
He could calculate the age of the Universe.
哈勃用他的数据
Hubble actually come out a measurement for that using his data
算出宇宙有20亿年了
he said the Universe about 2 billions years old.
这不对 我们知道地球要老一些
That was bad because we already knew the  Earth was old then that.
哈勃的方法是对的
Hubble was on correct track.
导致宇宙年龄错误的是
His formula for determine the  age of the Universal was correct,
他的测量不精确
but his measurement wasn't accurate.
这个误差给
And this discrepancy gave some scientists room
质疑勒梅特理论的科学家以话柄
to quibble with Lemaitre theory.
其他非科学原因也是
But other less scientific reasons
勒梅特的超级原子的不利原因
also may has contributed to Lemaitre's super atom
他是物理界的陌生人
be a strange of  the physics community
那是20世纪中叶
through while at first half of 20 century.
我想一个人参加科学聚会和
I think there was some distants to having somebody
宗教聚会肯定不同 但是
in the scientific compaign and in religious compaign, but
一些科学家们会不会因尴尬 不接受
did that made difficult for some scientists perhaps embrace them as much as
不在那个位置上的人的意见？
they would, someone not in that position?
有可能
Probably.
勒梅特的提议可能会使科学家惊奇
Lemaitre's proposal may have  left him astranged from that follow scientists
但庇护12世-教皇
but the Pope Pius the 12th
要中断这个理论 原因是
interpreted the theory as defective prove
理论与圣经里的起源故事想悖
of the biblical story of the Genesis.
勒梅特给教皇写信说 别这样说
Lemaitre wrote to the Pope and said stop saying that
这是科学理论
this is scientific theory,
由此得到的预测可以测量 检验
that makes prediction you can measure, makes many predictions you can test.
您的信仰于此无关
but your beliefs was independent those predictions.
勒梅特的理论可以测量 但如何检验？
Lemaitre's theory could be measured, but proved?
事情发生在数亿年前
It seems unlikely billion's years after the fact
不像是证据就要出现
the Big Bang's smoking gun will turn up.
除非证据被找到
And unless this smoking gun was find,
或宇宙间有其他理论提出
other theories of the Universe could be proposed
否则勒梅特的宇宙蛋 还得孵着
and the Lemaitre's cosmic egg would remain unhatched.
20世纪中叶  看起来宇宙蛋理论
By middle of 20 century, it seemed that the primitive atom theory
还有宇宙向外剧烈膨胀
with Universe expanding violently outward
从无限小的一点开始
form the infinitely small
不会得到广泛的认同
would never give wide acceptance.
哈勃不正确的宇宙年龄估算
Hubble incorrect estimation for the age of the Universe
使相互矛盾的理论
it allowed a competing theory
进入了剑桥的圣三一学院
to emerge for house of the Trinity College, Cambridge.
和大爆炸理论对应的理论
There was a tannable alternative to Big Bang theory
是稳态理论
the Steady state theory,
稳态理论使宇宙从永无止境到永无止境
which allowed the Universe to exist never lasting to never lasting.
稳态理论拥护
The steady state theory champion
静态的宇宙
the static universe,
宇宙蛋概念被驳回
that the primitive atom concept rejected
天文学家霍伊尔提出建议
Proposal by astronomer Fred Hoyle
基于元素的起源的一部分
It was build part of a theory of the origin of the elements
象氮 碳和其他100多周期表上的元素
Nitrogen, Carbon and more then 100 others in the periodic table.
在极端条件下 氢聚变生成氦
under extreme temperatures, Hydrogen fuses to form Helium
氦的聚变生成其他的重元素
and the Helium fuses in entire different heavier elements.
佛瑞德·霍伊尔 认为核聚变生成了新的元素
Fred Hoyle belive this nucleosynthesis creation of new elements
发生在非常热的星核中
took place in the cores of very hot stars.
那时那是一个绝对的惊人成就
That was an absolutely staggering achievement at that time.
霍伊尔的成就是教给我们
Hoyle's achievement was to teach us,
周期表氦后面的每一个元素
everything after Helium in the periodic table
都是星尘
it's actually star dust.
都是在星体上形成的
It is in the stars when this things were made.
这个理论不能算氢
But the theory couldn't count  for the formation of Hydrogen
和宇宙中的大量氦
and most of Helium of the Universe,
因为第一颗星必须要由已存在的氢形成
because the first stars must be made  by Hydrogen already in existing.
已存在的氢生成了74%的可探测的宇宙
This existing Hydrogen makes up more of the 74% of the detectable Universe.
霍伊尔没有正视这个问题
Hoyle side-stepped this problem
采用一种常用的神圣的信仰
by adopting a widly holy belief
氢和氦一直就是存在的
that Hydrogen and Helium had always existed.
事实上按霍伊尔的说法 宇宙是一直存在的
In fact, according to Hoyle, the entire Universe had always existed.
没有开始 没有结束是静态的宇宙
No beginning, no end, just a steady state.
简单地说 静态的宇宙是宇宙是一直存在的
In a nutshell, stationary state universe is  universe always been there
一直就是那个样儿 相同的平均密度
always looks like it does now,  always has same average density,
相同的温度
has same temperature.
有个小问题还不能解释
There was just a little problem unknow
人们知道宇宙已经膨胀了
which was people knew Universe was already expanding,
当物质膨胀时 密度就要变小
when the distribution of matter expands, because more dilute.
当宇宙长时间存在后 密度要小好多
Now, if the Universal very old, it would be infinitely diluted.
霍伊尔修正他的理论说
Hoyle fixed this fault by assuming that somewhere
宇宙在一直创造着物质
matter was always being created in the universe.
但宇宙的物质创造论
But the wholesale creation of the matter
物理学家们难以接受
was a hard pill to physicists to swallow.
霍伊尔有个反对者 俄国物理学家乔治·伽莫夫
And Hoyle had a nemesis source in the Russian physicist George Gamow
他信仰勒梅特的宇宙蛋
an admirer of Lemetrie's primitive atom.
伽莫夫通常出席那些讨论
Gamow usually present in these discussions.
他总是提出与霍伊尔不同的观点
And he always product disloyal questions for Hoyle's considered.
质疑静态的宇宙难以解释
Questions that the steady state is difficulty dealing with.
象霍伊尔一样 伽莫夫也使用原子问题
Gamow turn to atoms as Hoyle did,
支持他的争辩理论
to supporting his contending theory.
伽莫夫建议说 氢和氦以及其他元素
Gamow suggested the Hydrogen, the Helium and other elements
产生于宇宙最初的炙热的时刻
were created in first fiery minutes of the Universe
既大爆炸
in the Big Bang,
在温度高于数千度的
when the temperatures were thousands degrees hotter
任何星体的核心
than they are in the core of any star.
伽莫夫有好的想法 但数学不好
But Gamow was better idea man than he was a mathematics.
他把计算的事交给了
And he had to turn to this
非常聪明的毕业生--拉尔夫·艾舍尔·阿尔菲
phenomenally talented graduated student, Ralph Alpher
就是这个阿尔菲把这个想法
and it was really Alpher  who's really able to push this idea through
变成了结论
and come to a conclusion.
假如宇宙有同步早期元素的话
That if indeed the Universe had synthesized the early elements,
应该是氢是氦的大约10倍
it's should be roughly 10 times much Hydrogen as Helium.
与观测相符合 美妙时刻
And that match the observations. Fantastic moment.
阿尔菲和同事罗伯特·赫尔曼
Alpher with colleague Robert Herman
精化了勒梅特的有关
refined Lemaitre's prediction of
可检测到的生成随机热量的预测
detectable random heat from creation.
强有力地支持着大爆炸
A strong cluse supporting the Big Bang.
乔治·伽莫夫和他的学生有个简单的问题
George Gamow and his student asked a simple question:
假如大爆炸很热
If Big Bang was so hot then,
那么随后 大爆炸的余波
then the after the shock, after glare the echo
不可能象现在这样冷
of Big Bang can't be so cold now.
所以我们肯定可以测量到残余的东西
So the residual should be mesurable today. 902
很不幸在1949年没有合适的望远镜
Unfortunately, noone had the right telescopes in 1949
去测量宇宙生成时刻留下的热量或辐射
to measure the radiation or heat left over from the moment of the creation.
那时大爆炸理论还有个问题
And that time there were other problem with the Big Bang theory.
没有解释
It offer no explanation
氢 氦之后元素的起源
to the origin of elements beyond Hydrogen and Helium.
同一时间 静态宇宙论
At the same time, the steady state
广泛被媒体采用
goes on wide bright media coverage.
静态宇宙论被大众接受
The steady state theory was popular with general public,
是因为霍伊尔是平民化大师
because Fred Hoyle was master of the popularization
站出来推广他的古怪理论
just going on, marketing his wacky idea.
讽刺的是大爆炸是霍伊尔1949年
Ironically, the term Big Bang was coined by Hoyle in 1949
在一个大众化的广播电台提出的
during one of this popular radio broadcasts.
他随后使用这个有嘲笑意义的术语
He later used it as the term dirision.
我想他不喜欢他们之间的关系
I think he was dislike in their relationship.
他们谈事儿的时候目光都不接触
They did not see eye to eye on  most things will thinking about it.
我想他打了败仗
So I think Hoyle come out worse battles
他治力于
And I think he did more fighting for
他的观点被接受 但那是个人看法
his views than was merrited, that is a personal opinion.
弗雷德是个非常聪敏创新的人 我曾告他
Fred was very brilliant and innovating person. I just did point out him.
有人好有人坏 你只是不知道那个是那个
" Someone were good, someone were bad,  you just didn't know which was which. "
到了1960年
By the 1960's
哈勃估算出错的宇宙年龄问题
Hubble's inaccurate estimate for the age of the Universe
已被精确测量的数据改正
had been corrected to reflect more accurate data.
解决了大爆炸理论的一个问题
Resolving one challenges to the Big Bang theory.
看起来宇宙静态论和大爆炸之战
Still it seemed the battle between the Steady state and Big Bang
打了个平手
would ended draw.
接着 突然科学家找到了证据
But then, all of suddenly, scientists found the somking gun,
几乎和宇宙同期
a nearly old as universe as itself.
这个发现将一个理论打入了历史的垃圾堆
This discovery condemn one of the theories to the dust bin of the history.
500年来 科学在探索我们的归属
For 500 years, science has been on quest discover where we belong.
现在天文学家们尝试解开起始之谜
Now astronomers stuggle to solve the riddle of how it all began.
他们知道宇宙在轻轻地讲述
Little did they know the cosmos was whispering the answer back.
我们只是没有听到而以
We just couldn't hear it.
宇宙讲述着热量的痕迹
That whisper took forms of the left over heat
那出生时产生的热量的痕迹
generated when the Universe exploded in to being
勒梅特预测的辐射
The radiation George Lemaitre predicted was out there
但我们没有工具收听
but they had no tools to hear.
1965年科学家有了这个工具
By 1965, scientists had those tools.
大爆炸的余波 回音 残留
The residual , the echo, the after shocks after Big Bang
现在应该被测到
should be mesurable today.
但用了20年
But it took about 2 decades
使设备足够强壮
before instruments be come powerful enough
到可以捕获伽莫夫和他的学生
to clench George Gamow and his students theory
理论里提到的背景辐射
of this background radiation.
这个辐射的故事象个卡
The story on this radiation, it is like the keystone cards.
首先有伽莫夫和他的学生
First we had George Gamow and its students.
他们有理论 有数据
They had the theory, they had the numbers
但他们没有实验仪器
but they didn't had experimental apparatus.
接着有普林斯顿团队
Than we had group of Princeton.
他们知道伽莫夫理论 但只有原始设备
Well, they knew the work George Gamow, but they had very primitive instruments
不够灵敏
not sensitive enough.
普林斯顿团队里有物理学家罗伯特·迪克
The group of Princeton included to the physicist Robert Dicke
和支持勒梅特理论的同事
and some colleagues who supported the theory of Lemaitre
希望找到确凿的证据
and wanted to look for some solid prove.
我的老师鲍勃·迪克有方法
My teacher, Bob Dicke, had the idea to look for this radiation
寻找大爆炸留下的辐射
be left over from hot Big Band.
有两个聪明的年青人为他工作
He had two brilliant young people working with him
戴夫·威尔金森和彼得·罗尔
Dave Wilkinson and Peter Roll.
他说服他们做一个辐射表去找辐射
He persuaded them to build a deca-radiometer to look this radiation.
他也就是瞎碰
It was a shoot at the dark.
这两年青人做了一个
So this two young colleagues built one,
指向天空
point it in to air
开始了寻找
and started to looking.
从鲍勃·威尔森和阿诺·彭齐亚斯处传来消息
When the news of experiment reached at Bob Wilson and Arno Penzias.
彭齐亚斯和威尔森是科学家
Penzias and Wilson were two scientists
不是研究大爆炸的
working not on the Big Bang theory
是给贝尔实验室搞卫星通讯的
but on satellite communications for the Bell labs
在新泽西的含德镇
in Holmdel, New Jersey.
他们使用贝尔的巨大的无线电望远镜
They were using Bell's huge radio telescope
只是得不到清晰的电波
only they couldn't get clear reading.
得到的是静噪
Instead they got static nosie.
随机噪音是正常的
The nature stuff  it is a random noise.
噪音非常象是
And that nosie was very much like what's you hear
把收音机或电视放在空频道上
if you tuned the TV set or the FM reciver to unuse channel.
我们不想要这个
We don't  see we expected.
天线接收的电波太多了
The antenna actually get more radiation than it should have.
有人说我这儿有什么错了
Our clear respanse to that was there must be something worry here.
听到特殊的噪音
we get all extraordinary noise.
这强噪音怎么会事儿？
What was this strange noise?
哪来的？
And where it came from?
旁边纽约市来的干扰？
Aera interference from nearby New York city?
飞机的信号？
Airplane signals?
鸽子拉在天线里啦？
Pigeon dropping inside the horn of the telescope?
我们不怀疑物理学 .
We didn't doubts physics.
不管从哪里 肯定有来源
whatever was, had to come from somewhere.
但我真没主意这是啥
But we are real running out ideas, where it may be.
说实话 噪音来自各个方向
In fact, this mysterious radiations was  coming from everywhere.
天上的每个角度每个角落
Every directions and every corner of the space.
彭齐亚斯和威尔森快疯了
To Penzias and Wilson that's just crazy.
但他们不知道他们找到了
But Penzias and Wilson had unknowing they find
狄克和他的同事要找的东西
what Dicke and his colleagues were seeking.
伽莫夫  阿尔菲和勒梅特 预言的东西
What Gamow, Alpher and Lemaitre had predicted.
他们找到了证据
They had found the somking gun,
证明宇宙不是永恒的
that proved Universe wasn't eternal.
宇宙的创造动力是大爆炸
The source was the creation of the Universe, the Big Bang.
彭齐亚斯和威尔森与普林斯顿团队
Penzias and Wilson and the Princeton team
分别发布了他们的成果
published their findings in separated paper
于1965 天文学新论文
in the Astrophysics Journey in 1965.
他们的研究一夜之间粉碎了霍伊尔的宇宙静态论
Their reseach crashed Hoyle's  steady state theory over night.
最终大爆炸理论适于宇宙的谜团
Finally, thr Big Bang fitted in the puzzle of the Universe.
现代的大爆炸理论是显著的成就
Our modern theory of the Big Bang is  a remarkable achievement,
是我们可以建立模型
and it allows us to make a model of
看看宇宙是什么样的
what the Universe look like.
回到一切刚发生了的一瞬间
Rough back to ran everything was only  a tiny fraction second old.
高度压缩的质量和温度
And was squeeze to immense densies and temperatures.
形成了早期的密致状态
And from that very early dense state,
我们可以理解 勾出轮廓
we can understand and broad outline
宇宙是如何爆炸的 冷却的
how the Universe expanded, cooled
什么状态下第一个原子形成的
how some stage, the first atoms formed
什么状态下第一个结构形成的
how some late stage the first structures formed
生成早期的星球 星系 进而行星和人类
made early stars, galaxies, advencely planets and people.
1966年在布拉格的医院里
In a hospital in Belgium in 1966
勒梅特高兴得看到新闻
The dying George Lemaitre rejoiced with the news.
不止这些
It was not alone.
伽莫夫和他的团队也在喜悦中
Gamow and his team also felt justified.
我们曾为对宇宙的不同观点而气愤
We had been arguing for different view of the Universe
支持不同观点里貌似正确的一个
and allow behold that different view seemed to be the correct one.
总会被证实的
So that's always a vindication.
为了他们的发现
For the part of the discovery,
彭齐亚斯和威尔森赢了1978年的诺贝尔奖
Penzias and Wilson won the Nobel prize in 1978.
霍伊尔的宇宙静态论
The Hoyle steady state theory,
不再是人们的话题
had fallen out of favour.
他的核聚变理论未被抛弃
HIs theory of the nucleosynthesis was not rejected.
大部分科学家同意氢
While most scientists agree that Hydrogen
和大部分的氦由大爆炸产生
and most of the Helium were created at first the moment of Big Bang
象伽莫夫所说的
as Gamow believed.
所有的其他元素象氮和碳是随后产生于
All other heavy elements like Nitrogen and Carbon, were ceart later,
超星爆炸中的核心里
in the hot center of stars, in supernovas explosions,
象霍伊尔所建议的一样
as Hoyle suggested.
本质上讲 伽莫夫和霍伊尔都正确
So essence, both Gamow and Hoyle were correct.
尽管核聚变部分验证
Despite this partial vindication of nucleosynthesis,
死于2001年的霍伊尔
Hoyle, who dead in 2001,
始终不接受大爆炸理论
never accepted the Big Bang.
他不明白为什么人们都很热衷于
He could not understand why people were so enthusiastic
宇宙中有一个有限的开端
about Universe which had a finite beginning  in what I supposed he thought was a
发生在数亿年前
recent pasted a few billion years.
他只是不接受这个
He just never accepted it.
但除他之外的物理界全体一致地
But the rest of the physical community, with almost total unanimous
接受这个理论
did accepted it.
宇宙有起点这个事实
The fact we discoveied it has beginning
让我们有一系列关于起点的问题
allow you to know ask whole series questions about how it began.
有意思 真棒
That's kind interesting, that's kind cool.
你可以问什么时候开始的？
Because you can say when did it began?
现在和那会儿有什么不同？
How was different there and today?
那些变化影响了现在和那会儿
What changes the influenced between there and now
产生了我们所知的宇宙？
to creat the Universe we now know?
但接受大爆炸理论和想像它的影响
But accepting the Big Bang theory and thinking it fluence,
是两码事
are two different things.
理论的细节上还有问题
There were problems with the details of the theory,
爆炸的问题
expanding problems.
在20世纪的末期
During the last days of 20 century
科学家检验着大爆炸问题
scientists examined problems with the Big Bang
虽然理论被普遍解释
even the theory generally accepted.
大问题之一是
One of the biggest problems was
外太空的温度奇怪地一致
the temperature in outer space are strangely uniform.
物理学家不接受同一温度充满宇宙
Physicists didn't expanect the Universe would had same temperature
几乎他们看到的每一个地方
roughly everywhere they looked.
宇宙这么大
The universe is simply too large for
不可能这边的温度和那边一样
one end has same temperature as the other.
是的 换真一样
Yet it is.
就象你有放满凉水的澡盆
It is same thing happen if you had a bath full of cold water
要在一边加入热水
and you pour in some hot water in one extreme.
等澡盆水温一致需要时间
It's going be a while before the whole bath has steady water
因为热的分子需要时间
because it's take time to hot molecules to properly get cross
是全澡盆均匀分别
and to normalized whole distribution.
宇宙可没老到
The universe doesn't appear to old enough
可以让温度均等
for its temperature to has equalize yet.
大爆炸理论解释不了为什么遥远的两点
The Big Bang could not explain why which far away points
有相同的温度
have the same temperature.
80年代初阿兰·古斯有一个主意
In the early 80's, Alan Guth come up this idea,
可能宇宙的热容量很小
that perhaps universe came for very tiny volume.
很小的热容量
So tiny that within this volume
就有足够的时间使不同的点
early on there was time enough for these different points
交换而达到同一温度
communicate normalized the temperature.
在次只后 古斯理论上认为
Right after this moment Guth theorized that
宇宙的膨胀速度快过
the universe expanded even faster
光
than light.
快过宇宙的速度极限
Faster than the cosmic speed limit.
据爱因斯坦说那是速度的极限
The ultima speed according to Einstein.
理论指的是什么样的膨胀？
What Inflation refer to it is a theory?
是什么引发了大爆炸
what propelled the expansion of Big Bang.
被古斯称为膨胀理论
Guth called to his theory inflation.
在创立的早期时刻
At the earlyest moment of the creation, for instance
科学家相信有4种自然力存在
scientists believe that the 4 forces of the nature
包括引力和电磁力
including the gravity and electromagnetism
它们组合成一个超级力
they were acctually combined into a single super force.
在大爆炸中
During Big Bang
超级力分为四个已知力
this superforce split into 4 known forces.
但在分离之前
But before the split
当宇宙非常小的时候
when the Universal was incredibly small
爱因斯坦的物理定律
Einstein's laws of the phyics
包括什么都快不过光
including the one that is nothing moves faster than the light
还不适用
didn't apply yet.
可能那会发生了什么事
maybe at that moment something happen,
导致宇宙膨胀得比光还快
that cause the Universe to expanding  even faster than the light.
导致了宇宙的一致性
So fast that locked in the uniformity they had
就在宇宙还很小的时候
when the Universe still small.
我们不知道它精确地发生在什么时候
We do not know exactly when the Inflation happened.
很可能发生在
Most likely it happened
引力刚刚和其他的3 个力分开
when the gravity had splited from other 3 forces
在那一刻 其他的3 个力
but at that time other 3 forces
还在联合着
would still likely unified.
这个复合膨胀如果发生的话
This hiper-expansion, if it happened
会导致温度的一定性
would locked in a certain uniformity of temperature.
2001年6月3 日 美国国家航空航天局(NASA)发射了颗卫星
On June 3, 2001 NASA lunched  a satellite
可以测定
that could potentially determine one way or the other
古斯的膨胀理论是不是事实
the truth about the Guth inflation theory.
微波各向异性探测器任务
The Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe  or WMAP mission
是拍大爆炸余热化石的照片
plan to photograph the fossil random heat of Big Bang
彭齐亚斯和威尔森找到的
that Penzias and Wilson were found.
换句话说
In other words
美国国家航空航天局(NASA) 想要一个宇宙小时候的照片
NASA wanted to take a baby picture of the Universe.
他们可以和现在的宇宙做一参比
They could then compare it with how the Universe looks today.
2003年2月科学家得到了回音
In February 2003, the scientists got their first glimpse
一个宇宙小时候的照片
of WMAP picture of the baby universe.
当它38万岁的时候
when it near 380 thousand years old.
清晰的数据令科学家惊讶
The clarity of the data astonished the scientists.
当人们看到时的反映是
The reaction people had when saw this was:
天啊
Well!
和人们早期想像的一样
It really was the way people had speculating early on.
看来膨胀理论是对的
The Inflation probably happened.
对未经培训的眼微波各向异性探测器的图片
To the untrained eye the WMAP image
象一个罗宾的蛋
looks like speckled robin's egg.
对科学家来说 它就是字典
But scientists, it is a stellar rosetta stone.
那些模型代表要生长的种子
These pattern represent the seeds that later grow
已成为今天的星球和星系
into vast expensions of stars and galaxies of today.
古斯的膨胀理论的强力的旁证
Aside strongly supporting Guth's inflation theory
数据还给出线索于
the data also gave us concrete cluses
年龄 位置 形状和宇宙的进化
to the age, composition, shapes and evolution of the Universe.
几年以前 其他科学对天文学有看法
Up to few years ago, cosmology was quite think from the other sciences
很简单
simply because
理论比数据还要多
there were more theories on them around than data.
直到测到过去的数据
And it not until these satellites measured what was going on,
高精度地测到大爆炸很短之后的数据
shortly after Big Bang with such high precision
你可以描述一个又一个的模型
that you can describing one cosmological model from another
推演出众多的结果
and you can produced numerical results
象宇宙的尺寸 宇宙的年龄
about  the size of the Universe, the age of the Universe
宇宙膨胀的速度 宇宙的组成
the expansion rate of the Universe, the content of the Universe.
没有这些数据是做不道的
you couldn't do that before these data be come available.
以前只能是夹杂神秘的聪明的想法
Before there was a mixture mythology and clever thinking.
感谢象微波各向异性探测器卫星这样的现代工具
Thanks to modern tools such as WMAP satellite,
物理学家有了
physicists now have a model of events
大爆炸之后的事件的模型
just after Big Bang.
大爆炸之后百万分之一秒
Less than billionth of second after Big Bang
形成了比原子还要小的气泡
a bubbled much small than  a fraction of atom formes.
这就是宇宙
This is the Universe.
它不可想像的小
It is unimaginably small
不可想像的热
and unimaginably hot.
在气泡中 四种已知的自然力
Within this bubble, the 4 known forces the nature
引力 电磁力
gravity, electromagnetism
加上强的和弱的核力
plus strong and weak nuclear force.
组成了一个超力
were combined a super force.
引力突然从超力中分离
Gravity suddenly separated of the super force,
宇宙爆炸了
as the Universe expands.
宇宙爆炸了 冷却了
As the Universe expands, it cools
不知原因 散发出了能量
which somehow, sends out a burst of energy,
感觉到了宇宙的复合膨胀 阿兰·古斯建议
feelling the hyperinflation of Universe, suggested by Alan Guth.
这个复合膨胀保持了宇宙的一致性
This inflation locks in uniformity of the Universe,
由微波各向异性探测器图片证实
picture by WMAP satellite.
现在宇宙还没有一秒大
The Universe still less than a second old
接着超力分离为自然力
when the super force decaies separated  forces of the nature.
大约三分钟后 宇宙的温度
Roughly 3 minutes after the Big Bang  the temperature of the Universe
降到一百万华氏度
had droped to near 1 million degrees F.
冷到原子核可以形成
Colder enough for atomic nucleus to form.
形成了氢原子
The element Hydrogen forms.
部分氢聚合形成氦
Some Hydrogen atoms fuse to cerat the Helium,
伽莫夫和阿尔菲的假设.
that's proposed by Gamow and Alpher.
38万年后
380 thousand years later
光线穿越了黑暗
and light travel through the darkness.
由彭齐亚斯和威尔森找的的辐射
The burst of radiation that Penzias and Wilson find
发生在那时
happens now.
10亿年后
A billions years after Big Bang,
群星形成
stars took shape.
产生了氮 氧和碳等重元素
Producing the heavier elements like Nitrogen, Oxygen and Carbon
霍伊尔 的预言
as Hoyle predicted.
大约90亿年后
Roughly 9 billion years out,
质量和引力组合
matter and gravity combined,
完美的星类形成
to form a perfectly typical star.
压力导致核心发热
Pressure created heat at its core.
热量引发核聚变
This heat trigge thermonuclear fusion.
恒星诞生了
A star was born.
星际风暴吹散了残余的气体
The stellar outflow clears away residual gases.
所遗留的尘埃形成员环
a circunestelar disc of dust remains
最终形成行星和月亮
that eventually excrete into an entourage of planets and moons.
有一大块星尘
one of these lumps of star dust
被太阳系碎片反复撞击
after being pummeled for eons by residual solar debris
其温度高到足以使
has tempture warm enough to allow
氢氧化 水够成了大气
hydrogen dioxide, water to build up the atmosphere.
液态水积在星球的表面
Liquid water gathers on planet surface.
水下神秘的化学反应最终产生生命
Under water mysterious chemical reactions ultimaclly form life.
大爆炸137亿年后
13.7 billion years after Big Bang,
我们的宇宙以膨胀到方圆1560亿光年
our Universe is now 156 billions light years cross.
繁星遮盖天空
The sky full of stars.
太阳系有8个行星
Our Solar System has eight planets, more or less.
第三个行星上覆盖着碳级生命
The third planet is nearly covered in carbon based life form.
他们中的一些相信无限小的光子
Some are just realizing what infinitely small spects they are
也能做成大事
in the great scheme of the things.
你要是没听懂 没事
If you don't understand this process, that's ok.
他收集了百万人数前年的智慧
It is the culmination of million of human  brains struggling for thousands of years
来想通
to figure it out how the Universe began
我们在其中的宇宙的起始
and where man fits with in it.
足以使任何人头大
It is enough to overran to any one human brain.
认真想想大脑的进化
If I take seriously the idea that my brain was evolved, be able
从扔石头 拿香蕉到现在 真了不起
to throw rocks and take bananas and things thus, it's pretty remarkable
人类可以发现物理学
that we humans would be able to figure out much about physics
发现很多对我们祖先没有生存价值的事情
figure out  much about things that didn't  have survival value to our ancestors.
我觉得很惊人
Ya, I think it's quite stunning how well
我们人类能够在这方面有如此的进展
we humans have been able to make progress in this regard.
而不是去完善香蕉的过程
And not go completely bananas in the process.
这就是所有事情的故事
This is our story of everything.
我们的世界 我们的太阳系 我们的宇宙
Our world, our solar system, our Universe.
事情是怎样开始的
And how what all began.
这就是我们所知道的
It is what we thought we know.
工作还在继续 推演还在进行
It is a work in progress, the script still is being written.
我们来看看如何结束
Let's see how it ends.
纽约市
New York city.
美丽而平凡的秋天
A beautiful but unremarkable autumn day,
和以前一样 以后也会是这样
like thousands before it and thousands to come
直到秋天不再来临
until there aren't anymore autumn days.
想像一下 数十亿年之后
Imagine for a moment imagine travel in the future for billions of years.
人类文明已经过去
Pass the end of the human civilization
地球生物也没了
and the lives all living creatures on earth.
想像一下 五十亿年之后
Imagine we are 5 billion years in the future.
太阳的燃料已经用光
The Sun is running out the nuclear fuel that give its fire.
它在冷却 膨胀 在变红
As it cools and it expands and it reddens
离地球越来越近
coming closer and closer to Earth.
它吞食了水星和金星
it swallows Mercury and Venus.
地球水蒸发了 地球由融化了
Water on Earth evaporates  and the Earth be come melt again.
当燃料耗尽 太阳最终
When the fuel was gone, the sun's core ultimately contracted
由白巨星转变成白矮星
as transform from a white giant to a white dwarf.
太阳的外层的膨胀叫行星星云
The expanding outal layers of the Sun called planetary nebulae.
气体鬼怪般地坠入太空
drifting in the space as ghostly shrouds of glowing gas.
幸存的行星
The planets that's survive the process
象土星 天王星这些边缘星
the outer one like Saturn and Neptune
也被改变
are utterly changed by it.
行星星云吹跑了它们的大气层
The planetary nebulae blows away their gaseous atmospheres
只留下小小的岩石 金属核
leaving small, rocky and metallic core behind.
远处的行星
The distant planets
没有了太阳的引力吸引
no longer hold by less massive sun's gravity
坠入浩瀚的太空
drift in to the vastness of the space.
在其后的数十亿年
Travel billions of years after that
太阳留下的热量以辐射干净
and all remaining heat from sun has radiated out.
它又小又暗的表面
And its small, dark surface
冰冷得和宇宙其他地方一样
is same frigid temperature as the rest of the space.
太阳现在成了黑矮星
The Sun is now a black dwarf.
其后的数十亿年
Now billions of years later
由神秘的 刚刚发现的黑能量影响下
prepared by a mysterious, only recently  discoved dark energy
宇宙膨胀更快了
the Universe expands, ever faster
跑得到处都是
flying apart everywhere.
物质大规模的以分子级 摆脱了引力
On a grand scale and at a molecular one, the expansion overwhelms of the gravity.
所有的东西都分离了
And everything rips a part
不止星系 太阳系和星
not just galaxies, Solar System and stars
甚至原子
but even atoms.
最后物体自己一分为二
Finally, matter itself is torn sunder.
这个大剥离 我们宇宙的残余
This it is the big rip, the big restting piece of our Universe
传奇的暗能量 我们还没搞很明白
the legacy of the dark energy, that stuff we still haven't figure it out.
现在暗能量就是我们无知的代码
Rightnow, dark energy is mostly a code word of our ignorance.
这物质是什么 有人认为是一种东西
What this substance it is, some people think is sort of stuff, somepeople think
有人认为它含在爱因斯坦方程式里
it is a constant should be in Einstein's equations
还有人认为只能说明
some people think is just a reflection of fact
我们又把引力搞错了
we may got that gravity worry again.
现在宇宙末日大剥离理论在风行
Right now the Big Rip theory of the end  of the Universe leads the pack.
谁又能说这不是理论
Who can say if it is remain our theory
或又有新发现的挑战
or some new discovery will challenge.
我们没搞清楚的东西会传下去
The stuff we haven't figure out yet, goes on for ever.
放到我们的计划之中
one more blow to our centrality in the great scheme of the things.
不是说我们一无所知
But that does not mean that we do not know anything.
哥白尼 牛顿 爱因斯坦
Copernicus, Newton, Einstein
甚至阿尔菲 威尔森和古斯
even Alpher, Wilson and Guth
他们给我们留下了无尽的谜团
they have given pieces us of endless puzzle.
他们教我们如何去解谜
They help tell us how we fit in the picture.
承认组成你身体的每个分子
Recognize the very molecules that make up your body
构成分子的原子  可追述到
the atoms that construct molecules, a traceable
大质量星体的核心内生成
to the crucibles that were once to center of high mass star
传播富含化学物的东西到星系
and exploded there chemically enrich goods in the galaxy
丰富了原始的大气
enriching the pristine gas clouds
这是生命的化学
which chemistry of the life.
我们所有人都是关联的 相互间-生物的
So we are connected, to each other by biologically,
与地球-化学的
to the Earth, chemically,
和宇宙的其他部分-原子的
and to the rest of the Universe, atomically.
真棒
That's kind cool.
让我高兴
That makes me smile.
在此我真的觉的高大起来
And I actually feel quite large in the end of that.
不是说我们比宇宙好
It is not that we are better than the Universe,
我们是其中的一部分
We are part of the universe.
我们在宇宙之中 宇宙也在我们之中
We are in the Universe and the Universe is in us.
我们不是宇宙的中心
We are not the center of the Universe,
但我们身在其中
we are in it and of it,
想着搞明白这一切
try to figure it all out.
我们了解了很多
So much we know,
还有好多我们不知道
and yet so much we still don't know.
我们稳稳留在地球上
We hold on tightly our little planet
快速超越太空
goes hurries through space.
绕着太阳 绕着星系 绕着宇宙
Around the sun, around the galaxy, around the Universe.
别忘了观察
Don't forget to look up,
好多东西要去看 好多东西要去学
so much to see, so much to know.
咱们从哪儿开始？
where do we began?
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing